# 只不过叫法不同
Just that they have different names
# 第一个问题，有网友问
For the first question, there are friends asking about
# 黄酒，料酒和花雕酒的区别
the differences between Chinese cooking wine, huangjiu and Huadiao rice wine
# 黄酒 花雕酒是一类酒
Huangjiu and Huadiao rice wine are the same types of wine
# 只不过叫法不同
just that they have different names
# 黄酒一般都是产在绍兴
Huangjiu is usually produced in Shaoxing city in Zhejiang province
# 过去有什么 GYLS
There was a brand called GLYS in the past
# 现在还有一个新的品牌
and there is a new brand now
# 我忘了叫什么名了
I can’t remember the name
# 有这么两大品牌
There are these two brands that are popular
# 过去有加饭陈酿
In the past, we have those with rice added in during the fermentation process,
# 大紫檀的
fermenter made out of Burmese rosewood
# 黑釉面的
and fermenter with black ceramic glaze,
# 就是栗色的
which is a bit maroon colour
# 这个酒是比较好的
These are higher-quality wine
# 还有我们做菜
And when we cook,
# 常用的是大泥坛
we often use the ones in large earthen pots
# 那一坛大约20斤
It’s around 20 Jin in a pot (10kg)
# 稍微便宜点
It’s slightly cheaper
# 但是那酒非常好
But the wine is really good
# 是我们做菜当中
When we cook,
# 不可缺少的黄酒
this is something that we cannot be short of
# 说料酒
About the Chinese cooking wine (Liaojiu),
# 全国餐饮发展这么快
The food and beverage services in the whole country develops quickly
# 用量也很大
The usage of Chinese cooking wine is really big
# 有些调味品公司
Some condiment companies
# 就研发了一些叫烹调料酒
developed something called “cooking wine”
# 有的厂家是勾兑的
Some factories blend and dilute the wine
# 它直接买了一家黄酒
They just bought a type of Huangjiu produced
# 然后自己又勾兑了一些酒
and blend it with some other wine
# 稀释了
Dilute it
# 这酒就不是很好然后
This kind of wine is not really good
# 价格也很便宜
And also, the price is quite cheap
# 那种黄酒
That kind of huangjiu
# 它的酒醇味很重
has an intense alchol smell
# 等我们做完菜以后
When we finished cooking,
# 会留下很重的酒醇味
the dish would left with a strong alcohol smell
# 香味差
Upsetting smell
# 所以我们不倡导用这类酒
So we don’t really recommend this kind of wine
# 所以就选用了花雕酒
That’s why we chose to use Huadiao rice wine
# 特别香
It’s really fragrant
# 而且那酒香去腥提香
and the fragrance of Huadiao can remove some unpleasant taste
# 提鲜特别好的酒
It’s a really good wine for adding umami flavour
# 大爷说特别对
Da Ye is right
# 我曾经做菜的时候
In the past, when I’m cooking,
# 就用普通的料酒去做
I used ordinary Chinese cooking wine
# 做完料酒给我的感觉是什么
What’s the impression that the wine has given to me
# 还不如不放对
I would rather not put it in
# 我跟你说 不但这个菜没起到去腥的作用
Let me tell you, the wine didn’t remove unpleasant smell
# 反倒那个酒味
Instead, the alcohol smell
# 最后还出不去
can’t be removed
# 还闷到这里面
It’s been cooked into the flavour of the dish
# 闷到菜里面去了
Mixing with the flavour of the dish
# 而且就跟这些肉 什么东西不新鲜捂了似的
It smells like the meat is not fresh
# 所以说与其这样
Therefore, instead of having this awful flavour
# 还不如不放对
I would rather eliminate it